hi my name is Nicholas gray I work at a
company called our machinery and in this
talk I'm gonna talk about tools
development and more specifically what
we've done to speed up tools development
and make it faster and make our tools
better than before
I have long history of writing game
engines most well-known is probably the
bit squid and stingray game onion which
is actually the same onion it got
rebranded when autodesk bought it in the
last few years i've been working on a
new game engine called the machinery and
been trying to fix all the mistakes of
the past game engines that i made so in
this talk I'm gonna be talking a little
bit about the history we've had with bit
squid and sting ray our troubles with
tools why it's been so hard for us and
what we can possibly do about it and how
we attempted to fix it when writing the
machinery so first I'll start with a
brief history of our failures as when it
comes to tools the first words in a bit
squid our first idea about tools who
said we shouldn't write any tools at all
rather we should just expose sort of
public file formats like JSON files and
our users could just write their own
tools as long as they outputted this
file format they would work together
with our runtime and everything would be
fine it turns out this wasn't really
that great idea users actually do not
want to write all the tools themselves
you would think we would have figured
that out before starting this game
engine but we didn't really so we
quickly had to scramble and and address
this in some way so our first approach
was just well let's hack together
something quickly in WinForms this
actually is a pretty speedy way to build
tools you can just put in whatever check
boxes and buttons
and dialog boxes that you need but it's
to be honest it looks kind of ugly like
it's not it's not the nicest looks and
it's also turned out pretty messy we
didn't start with a clear plan of how
things should work in the tools and how
different tools should interact how
things like copy paste and undo and redo
and and drag and drop and stuff like
that was supposed to work so overtime it
got kind of hard to maintain and and it
got kind of messy but but to be honest
it worked pretty well and it's a fast
and nice way to build tools but we need
we thought we needed to do something
better so for sort of the next iteration
of tools for the bit squid onion we
decided to go with WPF instead the
reason we made this decision was like
that was sort of the recommended UI
toolkit from from Windows at that point
I think it still is but I'm not 100%
sure
and using WP effort or tools suddenly
looked a lot better a lot prettier but a
result of switching to two WPF in' and
moving away from this sort of hacky
approach we'd had before was that the
tools actually took a lot longer to
write was also a higher barrier of entry
WinForms is pretty simple to hack
together a tools pretty straightforward
but for to use WPF effectively you need
to know c-sharp you need to know sort of
the programming patterns of of c-sharp
and query style programming and stuff
like that you need to know WPF you need
to know Sam oh and there's a lot of
little subtleties that you need to know
and as a result of the tools so our
initial plan was we should rewrite
everything which just take all our wind
forms to convert them to WPF and things
would be fine but this conversion
actually took a lot longer than we
expected I think yester unit editor took
like six months or something to rewrite
and as a result we never actually
completed this rewrite so
some of the tools you see here so this
is sort of our launcher that launched
all our different tools and some of
these tools were rewritten to WPF and
some were not and we sort of had this
mix of tools built on top of different
frameworks which is which is not great
understand the cause for that was yes
that it took so long to rewrite
everything in in WPF then we got
acquired by Autodesk and one of the
requirements or wishes that all the rest
CAD was for our editor to be platform
independent and so that meant we
couldn't use WPF I mean we could try to
do something with mono but it didn't
look very nice and promising to go down
that route so we decided to go with
web-based tools it seemed reasonable
everything would be platform independent
sort of by default it would be built on
a web technology we also had the idea
that we could buy by using web
technology we could sort of reuse web
expertise there's a lot of people out
there who knows how to write you ice
using HTML and CSS and it could be nice
to use all of that and our tools would
run in the browser too which is kind of
nice but there were multiple drawbacks
with this approach our tech stack which
already was kind of complicated because
we had an engine using C++ and then we
have a scripting language for that
engine which was Lua and then we had
c-sharp to run our tools which targeted
WinForms in WPF so that was already kind
of complicated to this we now added
chromium to run the web tools QT
actually was used for the Windows system
and some parts like that we had
JavaScript of course because we need to
program chromium somehow we also had
some JavaScript toolkits I think we had
a bunch of them angular was one but I
think we had react there at some point
and some other JavaScript toolkit too we
had WebSockets to handle the
communication between the engine and
tool so it was a really deep heavy
and as a result of that tools took even
longer to rewrite because now there's
all these all these components that we
that we need to take care of and it
ended up being that we never completed
this rewrite either so not only did we
not rewrite or win from students to WPF
we didn't rewrite all WPF tools or all
WinForms tools to the web platform
either so at the end of sort of the
Stingray area we had this mix where some
tools were in WinForms some tools were
still in WPF in some tools were in the
web interface so even more complicated
at that point so to be to be honest bit
Sweden stingray never had good tools the
tools were always suffering and as we
started out with the machinery that was
one of the problems with that we really
wanted to fix because I think that every
time you you start writing in you and
Ian you try to want you you kind of want
to like atone for the mistakes that you
made in your last onion and find a way
of addressing them and fixing them and
that's sort of the drive to for for
making a new engine so we an identify
this as sort of a core problem so what
were the big problems one problem of
course is we keep kept changing the
frameworks the underlying UI framework
and that caused us lots of delays and
and lots of extra work yeah but there is
also so that cost made us lose a lot of
time writing tools but there was another
problem that tools just in general took
too long to write I remember on on a
number of occasions where I would add a
feature to the onion and it would take
me maybe four hours or a workday to add
that feature to the onion and then to
add tooling for that feature could be
like a week or two week two weeks just
to do the work it also need to be
scheduled into the sort of pipeline for
the tools programmers which means there
could be a month or something before the
before the UI was actually there and I
always felt like there was like this
weird disconnect here how
that it was so much easier to add stuff
to the runtime than to add stuff to the
tools and it always felt like the tools
were slowing us down and like holding us
back from from writing in awesome engine
so we need to fix that somehow a third
problem that we also had with with the
bit squid and stingrays especially as we
got into the web technology was bad
performance so I mean writing again
game engine is all about performance
it's all about how many characters how
much animation and physics and so on
rendering can you push and it's kind of
sad if your editor doesn't reflect that
so if you have really long startup for
your editor or if it doesn't just feel
snappy when you click on things it's not
nice so we wanted to make sure that the
performance of the tools match the
performance of the onion so how do we
fix this what what are the actual
problems that we need to address so one
of them changing frameworks so why does
it happen to begin with sometimes I
would say we're changing frameworks
because we made an initial bad decision
and using like platform specific
technology like winforms WPF could have
could be considered a bad decision maybe
it would have been better to go with QT
instead using web technology maybe that
was a bad decision too but it's kind of
hard to avoid all bad decisions you're
probably likely at some point to make
one or two bad decisions that will
result in you having to change
frameworks also even if you don't make
any bad decisions yourself you sometimes
get in a situation where technology that
you've used and sort of depended on gets
outdated or abandoned so there's a
number of different technologies that
that they get obsolete and they get put
into like the legacy scrap pile so one
of them that we used actually in
stingray was the Native Client the
Google Native Client and that cotton got
abandoned or deprecated and then we need
to find another way of handling that now
in theory you
if a piece of technology gets sort of
abandoned you could keep running on it
because you have the latest version of
it and you probably can still use it but
in practice that's kind of troublesome
because it means that since it's not
being maintained anymore by my the
people who actually made the technology
it means that you now have the full
responsibility of maintaining this
framework and that can be a big burden I
mean say you have an engine with like
$300,000 or 500,000 lines of code you
have to maintain that but but suddenly
you now also have to maintain like an
old version of chromium because you want
to keep Native Client and that's got
like a million or a million a half lines
of codes and do you really want to keep
fixing bugs in that and and also missing
out on on any new features that come
into like the main branch of chromium so
sometimes this just forces you to to
change technology through through no
fault of your own and the only way of
sort of avoiding that is to be rest less
reliant on these frameworks and be
really careful about what frameworks you
rely on and a durability of switching
them out if necessary another question
why did why did it take us so long to
write tools compared to writing engine
code
well we identified a number of factors
one is just like that every every little
thing you add to your engine needs UI so
you add a new parameter somewhere then
it needs someone needs to design of a UI
for that that piece it needs to be coded
it needs to be tested and so on so every
little every it's just a lot of work to
do every little thing there's also a lot
of features that you sort of expect in a
modern UI things like undo redo
unlimited undo redo you want copy and
paste to work you want to drag and drop
to work it needs to work with
serialization and saving and loading and
migrating of data and stuff like that
and all of these all of these little
things each each little thing takes time
to add and it also adds to your the size
of your code so every time you
you you i box and then you had undo and
copy/paste for that you add more code to
your your project and generally the more
code you have to lug around the less
agile you can you become and the more
slower everything becomes because you
have to manage out all that code and if
you want to make some kind of
refactoring you have more code to
refactor more code to debug in profile
and so on another problem specifically
with the way the stingray technology was
built was that we have this deep tech
stack and when you have a deep tech
stack like that it's hard to understand
where bugs are happening if you run into
a bug you don't really know well this is
this a bug in in angular is it in the
JavaScript code is in the WebSocket it's
an increment or C sharp or Lua or the
C++ there's just so many different
places to look so so the problem here is
really one of complexity the more
complexity you add to project the more
work you have to do for everything like
for finding bugs becomes more work and
finding performance issues becomes more
work
refactoring becomes more work adding
features becomes more work so complexity
is really your your big enemy that's
really what you want to minimize and
having all these layers and all these
components that are not really ours and
that we don't control really adds to the
complexity another problem with this
complexity too was that since there were
so many different components here only
the tool people really had a good
understanding of the tool stack and that
means that if a rendering engineer for
instance add a new feature to the
renderer they couldn't just go in and
add that feature to the UI because if
you I was too complex for them to to do
things like that quickly so the
development got very siloed and you got
the the tools team and the runtime team
and they were completely separate which
when you do stuff like that it often
leads to friction between the teams and
it also means that stuff that's
important for one team like like a
feature that's important to the
rendering team might not be as important
to the tools team so it ends up being
queued on some
you somewhere and you don't know
actually when it's gonna be implemented
and stuff like that and I just think
things run a lot more efficient when
everybody is sort of able to touch all
the code so the rendering engineer can
actually go in here and add it to the UI
and then maybe some UI programmer needs
to come in later and sort of pretty
things up a little bit but at least the
features there and and can be accessed
so people don't constantly keep getting
blocked by by other people third issue
the performance problems why did that
happen
I think a big part of that is that
standard web practices didn't always
work so so the way when you have web
programmers in they have their usual way
of doing things and that doesn't always
work when you're building a game editor
because game development has way more
stuff than your typical HTML application
like like I said when when it comes to
making game engines or games we always
try to push performance as far as it
will go and that means you're always
sort of running it at the brink of what
your computer is able to handle and if
you do things like and and that this
doesn't mean that you necessarily it's
not possible to do this in the web
browser web browser can do amazing
things and if you write things the right
way for the web browser it might work
but if you write it sort of the regular
the usual way of doing it it might not
work so what would open happen is that
some some of our UI programmers would
create a tool and it would look pretty
and it would run nice with like a
hundred objects in it but then as soon
as you put a thousand or 10,000 objects
in it it would would like break down and
run on it nice and fixing that was not
just an issue of like finding little
performance like profiling it and
finding little performance hotspots it
often required a complete rewrite of the
system like
and controls had to be virtualized data
had to be stored in a completely
different ways maybe we had to bypass
some JavaScript framework because that
framework wasn't didn't have a
performance mindset so the rewrite hood
was often the cost of the rewrite was
similar to writing the system from
scratch also the deep tech stack again
complicates everything it also
complicates finding these performance
issues and the browser when it comes to
performance issues and the browser it's
more or less a black box you don't know
oh I wrote my JavaScript code this way
and it's end digit into this bad path so
now everything runs ten times slower
than before and these things can be
really hard to know they can also change
from worsen to version of the web
browser so if you update chromium
because you need access to some new
features then suddenly you might have
completely new performance problems and
you need to investigate everything again
which make this really tricky to keep
keep a good control of the performance
so how do we fix all these things all
these problems well the thing with too
much stuff to write our idea there was
we can automate the lost little stuff so
stuff like undo copy/paste and stuff
like that if we define a standardized
data model which is the way we represent
the data in our application we can
define a lot of these operations on that
data model and that means that the UI
doesn't really have to be bothered with
it that much it doesn't have to do
anything specific to do undo redo it can
just talk to the data representation and
say well undo this action and then the
the data model can do it so that cuts
down drastically the amount of work that
needs to go into the UI step two what we
did we really didn't like this deep text
tag and all that complexity and the
problems with changing frameworks that
came with that so we decided to minimize
the text I completely use as few
frameworks as possible and also own as
much of the text tag as possible so
it's actually running on our code not
everybody else codes that means we know
the code we can debug it we can profile
it and we can understand everything that
goes on with it
make things explicit so instead of these
black boxes where you don't know what's
happening you can actually see what's
what's going on in there finally again
to handle this sort of busy work instead
of writing us for every little thing
we try to as far as possible sort of
auto-generate and all to populate the us
from data and so for example a graph
view or a tree view or a property view
we try to reuse them from between
different systems and just have them be
generated from the data so that way as a
programming you don't actually have to
write the UI it's sort of created for
you if you can use one of these
standardized views and components so
I'll explain all these parts as we go on
through this presentation but that cuts
away a lot of the busy work of just
creating us for everything it also cuts
down the size of the code which is
really nice too so start first with this
data model our way of representing data
and how we can use that to do things
like undo and stuff like that so our
data model we call it the truth kind of
shakily because it's we considered it's
the truth about the state of the project
it's where where you go to find out
anything about what the editor is doing
so all the data all the data that's
handled by the editor is represented in
a uniform way and then we can define
operations on it so the way the truth is
set up it's based on objects of certain
types each object has a type each type
is a number of properties and each of
those properties has a type so for
example a person object and might have a
name property that is a string and H
property that's an integer and then a
flag that's specifies what it's
registered or something like that so
this is kind of a it's kind of a JSON
like
model model with the way these
properties work except we have sort of a
schema for these different objects we
also have way well-defined ways of
representing references between objects
so and all they can refer to another
object and also sub objects so the
difference here is that sub objects are
objects that are owned by this object
whereas references are external objects
that this object just points to and that
changes how things work when you copy
and paste for instance for example when
you copy and paste you copy all the sub
objects but you don't copy the
references so it's nice to have that
explicit in the data model too so our
data model supports multi-threading
automatically and we do this actually in
a in a log free way and I'll be spending
a little bit about the detail of this
because it's important to other things
that we do in our data model too so the
way we implement lock-free
multi-threaded access is by dividing
change the step of changing the data
into two distinct steps so first you you
call write on the object that you want
to change and by doing that you will
actually obtain a copy of the object
that you can modify and all those
changes are local to this copy of the
object so it doesn't affect any readers
of the data they still see the old old
object and once you're done with all
your changes you call commit on the
object and it will atomically switch out
the old object for the new one with by
just doing an atomic pointer switch and
then all the readers after that all the
readers will see the new object so this
way the readers can read the data
without without locking and eventually
we clean up all the old copies with a
garbage collection procedure so undo in
our system is actually based on this too
which is why I presented this sort of
complicated multi-threading approach
first so undo works in a similar way the
only thing we do different for undo is
that
when we do an when we perform like an
undoable right we save the old object
and the new object so both these
versions in our current undo scope and
we can save these for multiple objects
because one undoable action might affect
multiple objects and when the user wants
to undo something we simply reinstate
the old data that we saved in this undo
scope we also have a system for
prototyping that's bill or prefabs
that's built into our data model and the
way this works is that any object in the
truth can specify another object to act
as its prototype and what this means is
that the instance of the prototype will
inherit all objects of all properties of
the prototype but if it want to it can
override some of them locally so we
could create an another instance of a
person object here that just overrides
the age for instance so this concept is
similar to the way like prefabs work in
in unity for instance for you you can
use a prefab and you can override
properties on it but the important thing
here is it's actually built in into our
data model so it works with everything
it's not just with entities but any kind
of data in the onion can be given this
like prototype treatment which is nice
so other things we can do sort of
because we have this and well-defined
data model is we can do really advanced
things such as real time collaboration
so multiple people on the network can be
working in the same project and the way
this works is that when someone does a
commit so they change something in the
date down we just compute the Delta
between the old and the new version of
the object and then we transmit this
Delta over the wire to our other
collaborators in the session and then
they will get those changes and they
will act enact those changes on their
data model and the data mode will be
replicated so this is an example of
this we have two people working together
here over the network a host and a
client and you can see that any action
that's performed by by either the host
or the client here in this level is
automatically reflected over to the
other person and again since this is
built into the data model it works with
everything and it also works with if you
extend our onion with your own data
types on your own your own kind of your
own data representation and your own UI
switch you can do with plugins all of
this will work automatically for for
your stuff too so sort of analyze this
this approach of using a data model in
this way what are the advantages and
disadvantages that we see well the big
advantages of course is we get all this
functionality for free we get undo we
get copy/paste we get serialization it
just works automatically not just with
our data but with other people's data
and plugins too and as we saw her it's
not just these simple operations like
undoing copy/paste it also works for
really advanced features such as
prototyping or real-time collaboration
so what are the drawbacks one drawback
is that this way of representing the
data the sort of key value format with
objects and properties it doesn't work
well for all kinds of data so an example
of data that's not that well represented
in this model would be long pieces of
text I mean you could do it you could
have an object where the string property
and that string properties just like 200
pages of text but it's not really a nice
way of representing that data because
the way our undo system works means like
if you change one character of that that
big document you have to make a complete
copy of all those 200 pages of text to
do the undo operation so it gets pretty
inefficient for that kind of data but
luckily that's not really the kind of
data that we deal with the
but in-game onions but yeah it's a
drawback of the system another drawback
I would say is that it's a pretty
complex system because it needs to
handle all these different things
prototyping multi-threading and it also
sits at the center of everything like
because because the whole point the
whole point of having a single system
that works with all the data is that
everything will use it so everything
will work the same way so there's really
no way for other system to opt out of
using the truth so if you wanted to
write for example a text editor in the
machinery it would have to use the truth
to be able to interrupt nicely with all
these other systems and so you would
have to figure out you could probably
massage it some way to find a way to use
the truth to still represent your your
text objects so that it would kind of
work but yeah you you can't really opt
out using this system and it's also the
complexity of the system makes it kind
of scary to modify the truth and add new
features to it because everything
depends on it
and the serialize the serialized data
that's stored on disk depends on it so
you might if you mess up you might
destroy people's same projects so it's
kind of a scary system to change you
can't get out of it even if you would
like to and and it sits in the center of
everything I would say those are the
drawbacks that's sort of the price that
you have to pay to get all this nice
stuff for free so next I'll talk a
little about our tech stack as I said we
really want to avoid being dependent on
on frameworks so we built most of our
tech stack ourselves we also want to
keep the tech stack itself as simple as
possible if you remember from the
Stingray tech stack we had a lot of
different language him languages
involved C++ and C sharp Lua and
JavaScript and we also had like scrapes
written in in Ruby and Python so big
ball of things so for the machinery we
decided to change that completely and
write everything in
even our Little Helper scripts are
written in C to the external libraries
we use is very limited so we basically
just use bulk and when it comes to the
UI we use Vulcan for rendering and then
we have the platform SDK as we need to
access to to get access to input events
like such as keyboard and mouse events
and then we have our own the API
abstractions on top of that a 2d layer
for doing 2d drawing and an input layer
which is our abstraction over the OS
input layers it's common for all
operating systems and then we have our
you a system on top of that which is an
immediate mode UI and then we build our
applications and editors on top of that
so our 2d drawing library it has regular
2d drawing operations such as stroke
react and fill rect etc whatever you
need for for drawing the UI but the ways
implement that is kind of interesting we
actually all these drawing operations
actually write data directly into a
single vertex buffer and a single index
buffer that will contain all the things
that we want to draw in the UI like regs
and text and so on and at the end we
just render these buffers with a single
draw call and if you want to learn more
about that I've got a link to our blog
that kind of explains how we actually do
this but the end result is our drawing
is really really performant since it's
just one draw call to draw the entire UI
clipping is done by the pixel shader so
when we want to do clipping if we write
our click breaks to the vertex buffer 2
and then the pixel shader will refer to
these clipping recs and and click the
data against it as it's written so we we
do no clipping on the CPU it's all
happening in the shaders which makes
that really efficient too so overlays
this is this is kind of a neat trick
which is why I wanted to mention that
so when we're drawing something in an
immediate mode UI it will sort of appear
in the order that it's drawn but
sometimes we have a desire to make stuff
appear on top of stuff that will be
drawn later for example if we have a
pop-up menu or a context menu we want
that stuff to sort of float on top of
the stuff that we draw after it and the
way we handle that it's not really by
doing some complicated layering
procedure stuff like that we just keep
two separate index buffers so we have
one index buffer that control contains
all sort of our main layered roll call
and then we have a separate index buffer
which we call the overlay index buffer
where all the popups drawing happens and
then at the end when we want to so we
just keep a single vertex buffer or a
single primitive buffer we called it
vertex buffer primitive buffer where all
the vertices go into but we keep two
separate index buffers and then at the
end when we're ready to draw anything we
just concatenate these two index buffers
so we just put all the overlay stuff at
the end after all the the regular stuff
has been drawn and since the index
buffer sort of contains all the actual
stuff that's being drawn by
concatenating the index buffer at the
end be the effect will be that all the
overlay stuff appears on top of all the
regular stuff so it's kind of a
interesting way that we use the the fact
that we're we're drawing everything
straight to buffers to do this overlay
effect one thing to note here is that
there are since we're drawing everything
including our overlays with a single
draw called our overlays camp actually
protrude outside your main window as
they can and windows for example so
popup menu will always be clipped to
them to the main window if you wanted to
if you wanted to show it outside your
sort of main rendering when you have to
spawn a new a new window to hold your
popup so that's kind of a different
technique but this is an interesting
interesting way of doing it the way a
way you can do it with just a single
draw call
even the overlays sorry UI as I said
before it's an immediate mode UI so that
means we're not like explicitly creating
or destroying UI objects that's kind of
what we mean by immediate mode instead
we have like a single call to draw a
control and handle the interaction so
for a button in for instance we have a
draw call and we call it with a
rectangle and text and it will draw a
button with that text in that rectangle
and if the button was clicked in this
frame it will return true and otherwise
it will return false similar with the
check box we call the check box and I
call the function to draw check box we
pass in a flag if the check box was
toggled this frame this frame that flag
will be toggled by the function so the
important thing to know here about the
immediate mode device is that these
buttons and check boxes that we are
drawing here they're not saved anywhere
after we've called this function there's
no memory that there ever was a button
or a checkbox in this place
so these controls that were drawing they
don't really have any existence no
permanent existence like the next frame
we might go a complete different set of
controls so the way we sort of keep
track of what what's happening with the
controls is that each control is given a
unique ID and that way we can sort of
keep track of which control the mouse is
currently hovering over or which control
the users interact and interacting with
when these controls don't really exist
permanently so pros and cons of this
approach using immediate mode yeah I
would say the big advantage is that you
get completely straightforward code flow
so if you want to know know if you have
like a debug somewhere like control is
showing the wrong State or control is
being too slow you can just step through
the code and see everything that's
happening from the call to button to
every part of the button being drawn and
the function returning you can see the
performance of it you can see any bugs
in it and it's just
you just go in there and do it whereas
if you have a retained mode UI which is
like the alternative to immediate mode
you have some part of the code over here
that is setting things up creating
controls destroying controls and then
you have some part over here which is
probably deep inside the framework where
the interaction of the controller or the
drawing of the control actually happens
and these parts are kind of separate but
what you do over here affects what
happens over here so if you have a
performance problems you kind of need to
figure out or a bug you need to figure
out like how these different parts work
together which is way more complicated
another advantage of immediate mode is
that there's no need to synchronize
state so so where is retained mode you
have to have like events getting sent
from controls and then you have to
process those events to change your your
data whereas here we're just drawing the
data when we draw the control we pass in
when we draw the checks box with PACs in
the current state so we send the data
directly from the application there's no
need of processing events or anything
like that which i think is a big
advantage a disadvantage that people
often bring up is that you have to
redraw everything and that that can be
expensive just redrawing the UI every
frame
I think that's less of a concern for a
3d application like a game editor
because you typically have a viewport in
there and that viewport typically wants
to render every frame anyway at least if
you have some kind of animation or
anything going on there
so you're not really wasting any any
resources but by also rendering the UI
every frame there are also also ways to
get around rendering every frame if you
need to for example you can render only
when you have actual input actions that
would change the UI so if the user moved
the mouse or if the user press the
keyboard you Yury render the UI and
otherwise you don't do it I actually
find that that with immediate mode you
guys is kind of easier to to get good
performance because you can easily match
you don't have to deal with anything
that's not visible on the screen
if you have a long list of items like a
thousand items in a list it's very easy
to like just figure out like Oh which
items are actually visible right now on
the screen like in the wreck that I'm
drawing this listing right now what
items can be seen and then you just
processed those items you don't have to
care about anything else whereas when
you're doing retain mode like if you're
doing retain mode in the default setup
if you have a list of 10,000 items you
have to somewhere create these 10,000
items and that might be really expensive
and the processing of those 10,000 items
might be really expensive so to speed up
performance you might have to resort to
some trick like oh I have to use
virtualized
items where I don't actually create the
items until they're really shown on
screen or something like that and and
you have to resort to tricks like that
in order to get the performance back
whereas wind immediate mode you're it's
very easy to do this kind of clipping
and just do just do the processing for
the thing that's actually shown on
screen so I find it a lot easier to get
a good performance out of an immediate
mode UI and then a lot of easier to
actually find where your performance is
going to but it is a new mindset and it
can it can take time to get used to and
the big thing with a new mindset is that
there aren't actually any objects to
talk to you because that's what you're
used from used to from a retain mode you
have a button somewhere and you can sort
of message this button and get it to do
something but in the medium mode that
doesn't exist so one example of that is
for example if the user selects copy in
the main menu if you have retained mode
UI you would find out which is the
current focused window or text field or
whatever and you would send that copy
event to that object now you can't do
that in retain mode cursors or in
immediate mode because there is no
object to send it to so how do you do
things like that you have to like sort
of wrap your mind around it this this
shows here the state synchronization
which is which is really nice we have a
number of different views here that are
all showing the name of this object and
to sort of synchronize the name between
this different views we don't have to do
anything because all these views are
drawing it straight from the data so
whenever it's changed in one view it
automatically gets updated into all
these other views and they will
automatically show this change without
the need for processing any events or
having any observer observable patterns
or anything like that which i think is a
great advantage of using this model as
an example of God shows you run into and
have you how you sort of need to change
your thinking when you're dealing with
immediate mode a problem that pops up
sometimes is if you have overlapping
objects so suppose that we have sort of
a graph editor where that spaced on
nodes and you can drag these notes
around and suppose that you have two
nodes two overlapping nodes like this
and you want to process mouse clicks now
if this was in retained mode we would
probably just loop over all these graph
objects that would exist in the UI and
check for mouse interactions but we
can't do that because the objects don't
really exist instead we sort of we have
to process these events as we are
drawing each object and the problem here
is that when we're drawing node one here
which happens before node two because
we're growing everything on orders so
the things we draw later appear on top
so when we're drawing node one here in
our immediate mode we don't know that
we're going to draw node two later so
node one temped just do a test like well
if the mouse is inside my rectangle and
the button is pressed
I should process this event because we
might draw node two later on top of node
1 in which case no two should actually
process this mouse event so how can we
fix this this when you're like
back in this retain mode object thinking
this might seem super super tricky but
we can actually fix this by introducing
a frame delay so the way we do it in in
the machinery is that we we keep track
of which object which objects the mouse
is hovering over so and we do it we
assign it at the end of the frame so we
check when we're drawing this this note
here we check if the mouse is in the
rect of the node and if it is we says
well the hover for next frame should be
our ID remember our unique ID is how we
identify this control in the UI and then
we check well if the Harvard object is
our object and the button is down then
we should process the event so let's see
how this works when we have two nodes
here like this so in this case the first
node would go here it would see oh the
rectangle is in in the mouse's in my
rect and it would set next hover the
hover that we should use for the next
frame - my ID then it would get then we
get to this check is the hover my ID and
the button is down the hover is not the
idea of this control yet because we only
said the next our variable not the hover
variable then it gets to know to the
node to text is the mouse in my rect and
it is which means no two updates needs
next hour to now point to no 2 so it
overrides what no one did and now next
hour is no 2 then we get to the end of
the frame which means we assign next
hover over to hover
so however is now assigned to no 2 which
means the next frame when we go through
this code again no 2 will see it will
hover is actually my ID and the button
is down so I should process process the
event so we had to do a frame delay here
where the mouse click is not detected
the first event to really hover is not
detected the first frame it only happens
in in the second frame and this is
basically the only way we can do this
because since no one doesn't know what
might be drawn after it we have to go
through an entire frame in order to
discover all the things that that can
potentially be drawn effort so it's it's
a different way of thinking and lots of
times this it's a different way of
thinking if you use to retain mode and
I've seen I've seen a lot of people
claim like well immediate mode UI seems
great but they can't do this and this
can be a lot of things sometimes it's
like drag and drop sometimes it's like
other stuff and and I find that that's
not true at all there's always a way to
do it in immediate mode but you have you
might have to do a trick like that there
like this like introducing a frame delay
like saving some data somewhere you have
to retain some data like we're we're
retaining the hover hover variable here
but you don't have to retain the whole
state of controls and stuff that you
just have to figure out what kind of
date that you have to retain and do then
do this sort of frame delay trick and
then you can solve all these problems
it's my my experience I haven't run into
anything that I wanted to do that that
can't be done in an immediate mode so if
someone says that to you immediate mode
can't do that I encourage you to
challenge that there are lots of stuff
that's that's really nice in immediate
mode that's the sort of problematic in
routine mode one thing is layouting I
really don't like layout managers that
you have in lots of UI frameworks I find
them really painful to work with usually
trying to get CSS to put controls in the
right place is is it's a pain in the ass
whereas if we're working in immediate
mode we don't really need a layout
manager to do any kind of layout thing
we're just working directly with the
rectangles here so we can just split
them ourselves and you do whatever fancy
algorithm on to split it like if you
want to equally sized columns we don't
have to like come up with some way of
tricking our layout manager into doing
that be a split split direct in half and
we have two equally sized call
so it's an example of here of this here
we want to do a layout like this
we are split off a rectangle at the top
to hold our header here we split up
split off another rect off that top rect
for the search field and we split off a
rect at the bottom to hold the footer
and then we use sort of a dynamic
splitter to do this split between the
two two areas here so this is super
straightforward in my mind super
straightforward super easy to understand
super easy to debug compared to trying
to get like a layout manager to get do
this kind of behavior doing custom
controls super easy to in an immediate
mode you are to do a custom control all
you have to do is to implement the
drawing of the custom control using all
these draw commands and destroy crack
filler eggs and so on and then implement
sort of the inputs interactions like
handle mouse clicks keyboard clicks and
so on and in fact there's no distinction
really between built-in and custom
controls our our building controls are
written in exactly the same way as as a
custom control would be and just to show
you an example this is how this drag
number control would be implemented I
won't go through this in detail because
it's it's a bunch of code but just to
show that it doesn't need a lot of code
to implement something like this you can
do it pretty easily
so in summary having the full control of
the tech stack like this it's really
nice it reduces the complexity a lot we
don't have to worry about framework
changes we can step through and debug
anything there's the same language and
API is used everywhere in the onion so
there's no artificial barriers
separating tools programmers from any
programmers anyone can go in and do
anything pretty much which I wish I
liked a lot the cons of doing things
this way building your own framework you
have to start from scratch like we
started with nothing and then we
implement the drawing primitives so
that's really starting from scratch
I would say that's about six months of
work or something before before you're
up and running with like a UI that you
can actually use but we found that that
initial cost is soon recuperated just in
how much time saving we have from not
dealing having to deal with wrestling
with the framework like wrestling with a
external framework and trying to force
it to do what you do at what you needed
to do you could start with an existing
immediate mode UI like they're there in
GUI for example that would be a way of
getting started way quicker that might
might be a good choice for you depending
on what your situation looks like
another con that you might not think
about is that I have doing things your
own like implementing everything your
own framework actually requires a lot of
design decisions when you use an
existing framework everything is sort of
decided for you you have a checkbox and
it works the way it should work whereas
when you write everything yourself you
kind of have to sit down and think well
how do I want a checkbox to work how
does it make sense for a menu to work
and so on you have to make all these
design decisions which depending on
whether that's something you're
attracted to doing or not attractive
doing that might not be the right
decision for you but you should be aware
of that there's a fair amount of
thinking and work that goes into that
and also as I said it kind of requires
to rewrite rewire your brain a lot to
think about UI this way to do immediate
mode so the final thing we're doing here
generating you eyes as I said before the
idea here is we want to reduce the work
we don't want to create you guys for
everything we want to try that
automatically somehow a typical example
of that is a properties panels and I
think this is something that a lot of
editors would do they would drive their
property panel they would they wouldn't
implement it for each object it would
sort of drive it from data and and
that's what we do and we use a property
panel as sort of our default object
editor and the way it works is that we
loop over all
properties of an object and we draw an
appropriate control for each of these
properties so for boolean might be a
checkbox for a string it might be a text
box and so on and now using the default
control might not work for everything
for example things like color you might
want to have a custom control for that
so how do we do that and we get the we
get all these properties from the truth
by the way since we have a standard data
model for that so to handle custom
properties we use the system that we
called aspects and basically it's just a
callback a function callback identified
by an ID so each system can define an
aspect like this so the property the
property tab has defined a callback
that's identified by an aspect called
aspect custom properties so we can if we
want an object in the truth to be drawn
in a special way in the property panel
all it has to do is to implement this
aspect and then when we go through all
the objects here we check them all does
this object have a special aspect for
interacting with the property panel and
if it does that aspect will be called
and if it doesn't it will get the
default panel so this is an example of
that for a vector3
again I won't go through the code it's
just showing that it's pretty easy to to
do this and the nice thing about this is
that every control every everything gets
a UI by default because we map the
standard controls to the UI but then you
can go in and customize it with a
special control if you really need to
but we take this this approach of using
generated UI is even further not it's
not just for properties we use it for
previews for instance so this is
controlled by an aspect again so any
object that want to be able to be
previewed just adds a preview aspect to
the object type in the truth and then
that preview aspect takes care of
drawing the object in this preview
window spawning entity is drawing UI
playing sounds and so on whatever is
needed to preview that kind of object we
use the same thing
or trees so by default here we would
render by default to render a tree view
of an object we would just render all
sub only access children but if an orbit
was customized that it can int it can
implement the tree view aspect and do
its own custom tree drawing so here's an
example of a full UI using all of this
so this is our animation state machine
editor as you can see there's a lot of
pieces of UI here but all these pieces
are actually standardized so we have a
tree view here that's our standardized
tree view control we didn't implement
anything special for the state machine
we have a graph view that's our standard
graph view control and the state machine
is just implementing an aspect of it to
define how its objects get represented
in this graph view same with the
property substantive properties control
and we have a preview control here which
is our standard preview window as I
mentioned earlier so this way we can put
together a really complex UI by just
reusing all these different parts which
is really nice so conclusion here I
would say that creating UIs in this way
in this system feels a lot faster we no
longer feel blocked by UI tasks and in
fact we could build our entire engine
with the UI with editor and everything
by two people in two years which i think
is really good our data model it's
awesome to get all this stuff for free
but it's also a little bit scary how
it's a central piece of technology
that's kind of complex and it's getting
more complex with every piece of
functionality that gets added to it I
think using aspects the way we are it's
a really great way of customizing object
behavior and I definitely recommend that
implementing things yourself is a lot of
work functional design as I said but I
think the payoff payoff is great not
being dependent of frameworks being able
to debug and profile everything and
being in control I would say that we're
missing some features that you would
find in a full fledge toolkit we don't
have supported for right-to-left text
for instance for
localization but I don't worry so much
that we don't have a ton of features as
long as these features would be would be
easy to add when we need them so at the
point where we start needing this I'm
pretty sure we could implement it easily
that's the whole point the keys to
keeping things simple and being agile
and I think there's a danger of having
lots of features but having a complex
system that is so complex that you don't
actually have time to use these features
as an example in stingray we decide we
use the web technology and stuff to be
platform-independent
but they never had time to support any
other platform than Windows and we had
right-to-left text that we needed but we
never had time to really start on
localization of the editor at all so I
think like you have to be really careful
about how you're spending your time and
it's more important to be simple and to
be agile than to have features that
you're not using yet and all in all
we're really super happy with the way
things are going and the speed with
which we've been able to develop you
guys and it feels fun to make tools and
you guys for the onion which it didn't
really do before and I'm really pleased
and happy with that so this would be the
time where I would ask for questions I
can't really do that now since we're in
lockdown mode but if you have any
questions tweet me and my Twitter handle
there we have a podcast and our
machinery podcasts that I recommend you
can listen to if you want to find out
more stuff that we're doing we also have
a blog available at our website
our machinery calm and feel happy to
read that and contact us if you're
interested in looking at the onion or
using it